<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<effects>  
  <effect>
    <name>Alchemical Solvent</name>
    <group>Coating</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This solvent, covering one square foot per dose, will remove
      everything in the “Coating” effect group.  It can also
      release a victim of an Entangle.  Once used, the entire
      dosage is consumed.
    </description>
    <contact>5</contact>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Amnesia</name>
    <group>Greater Command</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      Victims of this elixir cannot remember anything that
      occurred 60 minutes prior to its administration.

      In the place of the now inaccessible memories is a blank
      spot within the memory.

      Victims can be aware that they cannot remember anything for
      that period and may reasonably assume that they have been
      given an Amnesia elixir.

      For the first ten minutes, beginning at the time of the
      Amnesia’s administration, the Amnesia elixir may be
      countered and memories of the period returned by either a
      Dispel or a Purify.

      After the ten minute period, Amnesia becomes incurable and
      the recipient permanently loses their memory of the 60
      minute period.

      Biata and stone elf role-playing racial skills cannot remove
      the effect of an Amnesia elixir, nor can any NPC mind
      abilities.

      Neither a Life spell nor a Resurrection will restore the
      memory of the recipient even if it occurs during this ten
      minute period.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <deadline>Ten minutes</deadline>
    <elixir>45</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Antidote</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      One dose of an Antidote will remove all lasting effects in
      the Alteration effect group (Feeblemind, Hallucinate,
      Intoxicate, Laugh, Nausea, Paranoia, and Vertigo). It does
      not matter how those effects were caused.

      For example: Finther is hit by a Feeblemind gas thrown by
      his enemy Vorin. He sits on the ground and plays with
      daisies. While he is on the ground, a ghoul hits him for “3
      Nausea.” He is now vomiting while playing with
      daisies. Finally, someone throws a Paralysis spell at him
      and he becomes paralyzed.  Darlissa runs over and feeds
      Finther an Antidote. Both the Feeblemind and the Nausea are
      removed; however, this does not cure the damage caused by
      the weapon nor does it remove the paralysis.
    </description>
    <elixir>20</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Awaken</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This effect awakens the recipient from a Waylay and removes
      all Command effects but not Greater Command effects.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I command you to Awaken.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>20</potion>
    <scroll>20</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Banish</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Line-of-sight</duration>
    <description>
      This spell forces a creature not native to the current plane
      to return to its home plane or expend a significant amount
      of energy remaining where it is. Creatures already on their
      home plane are immune to the Banish effect.

      This spell usually only affects elementals, fey, and
      extraplanar creatures (NPCs should check the creature type
      on the monster card), but may affect other types at the
      discretion of the Plot Committee. PCs may be affected by
      this spell in certain circumstances to be announced
      beforehand by the Plot Committee.

      Lesser elementals, lesser fey, and lesser extraplanar
      creatures affected by this spell instantly dissipate as if
      slain, leaving behind anything carried. An affected creature
      with the ability to Rift In or Rift Out may not use that
      ability until the next game-day.

      For example: Sparky is a Lesser Flame Elemental who has
      decided to visit his “friends” on Fortannis on Friday
      night. Belthivis thinks little of this and casts a Banish at
      the creature, who dissipates instantly, unable to visit
      Fortannis again until the next game-day (usually the next
      night, after Logistics).

      Greater elementals, greater fey, and greater extraplanar
      creatures affected by this spell take 50 points of
      damage. If slain by this damage, the affected creature
      cannot Rift In or Rift Out until the next game-day.

      This spell usually has no effect on normal living or undead
      creatures, but, like all spells, will still remove a Spell
      Shield or Reflect Magic.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I Banish you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Berserk</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect drives the victim into an insane mindless
      killing fury, causing the victim to attack all creatures in
      the vicinity, starting with the closest, friend or foe.

      The victim will use no daily Game Abilities except basic
      weapon skills (including shields and claws). A character
      with no weapon skill will simply scream in rage and run
      around with fists clenched.

      The victim of a Berserk will not throw spells or alchemy and
      will not use Resists, Dodges, Banes, Cloaks, Parrys, or any
      other defensive skill. Spell Protectives will still work as
      normal.

      A person under the effects of a Berserk will not stop to
      give a Killing Blow or search a victim, but will immediately
      turn to find something else to attack once an attack victim
      falls.

      For example: Ena is hit by a Berserk effect thrown by a
      monster. Ena uses her weapon to attack the nearest
      person. She is able to use her proficiencies but is so
      mindless that she cannot think to take advantage of any
      Critical Attacks, Slays, or other daily skills that she
      could use. She is hit by a troll for enough damage to take
      her down, but cannot think to use her Parry against it.

      It lasts ten minutes and like all Command effects can be
      resisted by a Resist Command or removed by Break Command,
      Awaken, Dispel, or Purify. Only one Command effect may be
      active on the victim at any one time. The most recent
      Command effect takes precedence.
    </description>
    <remove>Awaken</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>45</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Bind</name>
    <group>Binding</group>
    <duration>Line-of-sight</duration>
    <description>
      This spell snares the arms of its victim, binding them
      straight to its sides. The victim may talk freely, but may
      not use any Game Abilities requiring the use of arms,
      including using a weapon or shield, casting a spell, or
      activating a gas globe. The victim may walk, run or leave
      the combat area as desired.

      This spell does not prevent the victim from being searched
      or being given a Killing Blow, although a moving victim is
      unlikely to allow either action.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Release</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With mystic force I Bind you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>15</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Bless</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This spell gives the recipient 5 extra Body Points beyond
      the character’s maximum. These points are the first Body
      Points lost to damage.

      In order to be affected by a Bless, the individual must be
      at 1 Body Point or higher. If not, the player should say “No
      Effect.” This spell cannot be used to revive an unconscious
      person.

      A Bless spell will be ineffective if cast upon a character
      who does not have at least one Body Point, causing the
      target to call “No Effect” as they are an invalid
      target. The Body Points added by a Bless spell act in all
      other ways as per normal Body Points (including interaction
      with other carrier effects).
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of a Bless.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>2</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>10</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cause Critical Wounds</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 20 Body Points of damage. It does not
      affect armor.

      Against undead, this spell cures 40 Body Points.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Cause Critical Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>30</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cause Damage</name>
    <group>Damage</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This substance inflicts 5 points of body damage. It does not
      affect armor.
    </description>
    <elixir>10</elixir>
    <gas>15</gas>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cause Light Damage</name>
    <group>Damage</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This substance inflicts 2 points of body damage. It does not
      affect armor.
    </description>
    <elixir>5</elixir>
    <gas>10</gas>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cause Light Wounds</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 2 Body Points of damage. It does not
      affect armor.

      Against undead, this spell cures 4 Body Points.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Cause Light Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>5</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cause Mortal Wounds</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 30 Body Points of damage. It does not
      affect armor.

      Against undead, this spell cures 60 Body Points.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Cause Mortal Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>40</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cause Serious Damage</name>
    <group>Damage</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This substance inflicts 10 points of body damage. It does
      not affect armor.
    </description>
    <elixir>20</elixir>
    <gas>25</gas>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cause Serious Wounds</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 10 Body Points of damage. It does not
      affect armor.

      Against undead, this spell cures 20 Body Points.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Cause Serious Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>20</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cause Wounds</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 5 Body Points of damage. It does not
      affect armor.

      Against undead, this spell cures 10 Body Points.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Cause Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>2</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>10</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Chaos Blade</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the recipient to transform a weapon into a
      temporary chaos-enchanted blade.

      The recipient chooses when to use the Chaos Blade, and
      announces the total damage of the swing while saying “chaos”
      instead of “normal” or “silver.”

      It may be used on any weapon, even bows and crossbows.

      This spell lasts until dispelled or ten minutes pass,
      whichever is first.

      Note that this spell only affects creatures who are harmed
      by chaos and does not heal those normally healed by
      chaos. Damage bypasses any armor on the target and does
      direct Body Point damage.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to grant you a Chaos Blade.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Chaos Storm</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <description>
      At the time of casting, the caster plants both feet. As long
      as both feet remain planted, the verbal is stated, and the
      spell is not disrupted as per normal spell rules, the caster
      may throw packets. While the spell is in effect, the caster
      can perform no other skill nor cast any other spell.

      Each packet thrown counts as a separate spell which causes
      10 points of chaos damage, which goes directly into Body
      Points and is not blocked by armor. The caster must say
      “Chaos Storm” with each packet thrown.

      This spell will only damage creatures who are damaged by
      chaos and may not be used to heal undead creatures. Like all
      spells, this spell will use up a Spell Shield or Reflect
      Magic even if the target is immune to the spell’s effect.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to summon a Chaos Storm, Chaos Storm, Chaos Storm...</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Charm</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell makes the victim view the caster as his or her
      best friend in the world. No amount of logic or role-playing
      will convince the victim that they are indeed charmed, and
      any order given will be justified and make perfect sense in
      the mind of the victim. The victim will not remember the
      casting of the spell.

      An attack on the victim by the caster’s companions will not
      immediately break the charm but if the caster does not
      attempt to stop it and if no good reason is provided for the
      attack, the charm may be broken. A direct attack by the
      caster will always break the charm, as will attempting a
      Killing Blow. An order to kill yourself would also break the
      spell.

      A victim of this spell will not do anything absolutely
      contradictory to their own race or nature (such as cast
      necromancy). If given an order to attack their own party,
      the victim would have to also be given a very good and
      convincing reason. (The victim will, however, protect the
      new “friend” from attacks, no matter who from.)

      This spell only works on creatures that have a mind as
      defined by the game. Many creatures (such as lesser undead,
      golems or insects) do not have a mind that can be affected
      by this effect. Further, the victim must understand the
      language of the caster in order to follow the orders.

      Unlike Dominate, this effect does not turn the victim into a
      mindless robot, but does require the victim to stay by his
      or her new “friend” and follow all “suggestions” given by
      the caster. Unlike Enslavement, the victim is unaware of the
      effect.

      Victims cannot refuse to obey orders with the explanation
      that they “wouldn’t do that even for my best friend.” This
      spell overwrites the logic of the brain. If your new “best
      friend” tells you to hand over all your items, you will do
      so without question.

      When the spell’s duration ends, the victim remembers
      everything that happened except the actual casting of the
      Charm spell, and will almost always realize that he or she
      had been charmed.

      This effect can be removed by an Awaken, a Break Command, a
      Dispel, or a Purify. Note as well that only one Command
      effect may be active on the victim at any one time. The most
      recent Command effect takes precedence. This spell is not
      strong enough to override any Greater Command effect such as
      Enslavement.
    </description>
    <remove>Awaken</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I command you to be Charmed.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Circle of Power</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>One hour</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the caster to inscribe a Circle of
      protection against harm. Before casting the spell, a
      visible, physical representation of the Circle must be drawn
      in the dirt or represented by something physical like chalk,
      a ribbon, or some string. This physical representation is
      in-game and can be erased, moved or stolen at any time
      before the spell is cast.

      The caster must be fully within the completed Circle. This
      spell cannot be cast until the phys rep is complete. Anyone
      who steps on the phys rep while it is being raised will be
      pushed inside or outside of the Circle (player’s choice),
      along with all possessions.

      The phys rep does not have to make a perfect circle, but if
      the phys rep is too big, or if the ends are not almost
      touching, then the spell is blown.

      A Circle of Power stretches up to 6' in radius and 10' tall
      and is a cylindrical dome with a flat bottom. The Circle has
      about the same amount of friction as a normal wall or floor,
      although objects and creatures cannot lean against, rest
      against, or be placed on top of the Circle.

      Larger Circles can be made by having multiple spell casters
      casting the spell simultaneously. For example, a Circle up
      to 12' radius and up to 20' height may be made by two
      casters. The casters must say the incant at the exact same
      time for this to be effective.

      It is possible to surround a Circle with a larger Circle,
      but a smaller Circle can not be placed inside an already
      existing Circle. A Circle inside of another Circle is
      considered its own space; you are not considered to be
      inside the exterior circle.

      Nothing may enter or leave the Circle once it is cast,
      including spells, thrown gasses, weapons and
      creatures. Traps placed near the Circle will not affect
      anyone or anything inside; similarly, traps within the
      Circle will not affect anyone outside the Circle.

      Spells may be cast within the Circle, but cannot be thrown
      through the Circle. Air may pass through, but other gasses
      may not.

      A gaze attack such as a Vampire Charm can be effective
      through a Circle of Power. A Gypsy Curse can also be used
      through the Circle. Creatures inside a Circle are still
      considered inside Line of Sight.

      The spell lasts for one hour, but may be dropped by the
      caster at any time if he or she touches the Circle and
      states “circle down.” If there is more than one caster in a
      larger Circle, any one of the casters may drop the
      Circle. The statement “circle down” is out-of-game, although
      any observers who hear the statement are aware that the
      Circle was dropped, and they might know who dropped it.

      The Circle will also go down if the caster leaves the Circle
      magically or dies (needing a Life spell). If there is more
      than one caster, the Circle will remain up until all of the
      casters leave or die.

      The Circle is not affected by a Dispel.

      This spell can also be used to create a Circle that can be
      used for the casting of a Formal Magic ritual. If a ritual
      is started within one minute of the Circle being cast, the
      duration of the Circle of Power is extended to one hour and
      one minute.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I build a Circle of Power.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Confine</name>
    <group>Binding</group>
    <duration>Line-of-sight</duration>
    <description>
      This spell snares the arms of its victim, binding them
      straight to its sides, and immobilizes the victim
      completely. The victim may talk freely, but may not use any
      Game Abilities requiring the use of arms or legs, including
      using a weapon or shield, casting a spell, or activating a
      gas globe. The victim may not walk, run, or be moved in any
      way. This victim can be searched and can be given a Killing
      Blow.

      The main distinction between a Confine and a Web is that
      certain monsters that can break free from a Web cannot
      necessarily do so from a Confine.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Release</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With mystic force I Confine you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Control Undead</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the caster to control one lesser undead
      for ten minutes. Tasks may not involve anything a trained
      animal could not be taught: “Guard this” is fine, but “Count
      all the leaves on the tree” requires sentience and will not
      work. This spell will also remove all Turn Undead
      effects. When used on an undead of higher than “low
      intelligence,” it will force the affected undead to become
      temporarily able to understand only simple commands.

      The most recent Control Undead effect takes precedent if
      there is a conflict.

      This spell will not affect a living target, although it will
      remove a living target’s Spell Shield or Reflect Magic.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Control Undead.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Create Undead</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell only works on a corpse that has neither
      previously been animated nor is permanently dead. It will
      pull the character’s spirit back to reanimate its former
      body. The resulting zombie will then follow the caster’s
      commands as if a Control Undead spell had been cast upon it.

      Note that this spell must be cast within the five-minute
      period between a character’s death and the point where the
      spirit heads to the Earth Circle for resurrection.

      This spell will not affect a living target, although it will
      remove a living person’s Spell Shield or Reflect Magic.

      If you are raised, you cannot then “choose to die.”

      The zombie uses none of the skills that the character
      has. It inflicts two points of damage with any weapon
      attack. It cannot cast spells nor converse (although it may
      be commanded to parrot a particular phrase given it by the
      caster).

      If the newly created zombie has no weapon, then it will be
      able to attack with “claws” (short sword-sized weapons
      covered in red duct tape) doing two points of damage
      each. The caster must provide the physical representations
      for the claws.

      The zombie created will have half the Body Points the victim
      had in life (not including enhancement spells such as
      Bless), as well as any armor that is left on the corpse. Any
      missing or withered limbs will also be temporarily
      regenerated for the duration of this spell.

      The zombie is considered Undead in every way, and has the
      standard immunities and vulnerabilities of Undead. These
      include being immune to Alteration, Command, Death, Ice,
      Poison, Paralysis, and Waylay.

      In addition, the creature will take double damage from
      healing and be healed double by necromancy. The zombie will
      have no metabolism and will be affected by undead-specific
      spells such as Turn Undead and Sanctuary.

      The creature’s visual appearance does not change
      immediately, but the victim will move slowly, shambling
      along, as a zombie should.  (A zombie fights with normal
      speed but cannot move fast enough to chase anyone who runs
      away.)

      If the zombie is reduced to zero Body Points, or if the
      ten-minute duration of the spell is met, then the body and
      the spirit return to the condition they would have been in
      had the Create Undead not been cast.

      If during the five-minute Death Countdown you are “killed”
      as the undead and then given a Life spell, you will reawaken
      alive but with no knowledge of your time spent as an undead.

      For example: Poor Terin falls fighting against a necromancer
      and his undead abominations. He is at -1 Body Points. He
      lies there for a minute but no one comes to him with First
      Aid. (Terin is keeping track of the time.) At the end of the
      minute, he is now dead and all of his Spell Protectives
      gone. The necromancer sees Terin and then casts a Create
      Undead spell on him. Terin rises as a zombie. He attacks his
      party, and the battle lasts more than two minutes. During
      this period, they throw Life spells at him, but they have no
      effect because he is a zombie. Finally, they knock him back
      down to zero Body Points. He is no longer a zombie and is
      merely a dead body. Since the five minutes since the time of
      his death are not up, a Life spell will still save Terin,
      but because the one minute period for First Aid has expired,
      he can no longer be saved by First Aid or a curing spell.
      The death countdown did not stop when Terin became a zombie.

      The ten-minute spell duration cannot be extended by any
      means, even by Formal Magic.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Create Undead.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cure Critical Wounds</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell restores up to 20 Body Points but never more than
      a character’s maximum.

      It restores an unconscious or dying character but does not
      resurrect a dead one. It inflicts 40 Body Points of Damage
      to undead creatures.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Cure Critical Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>30</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cure Disease</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will cure a character infected with Disease. If
      cast upon an undead, it will make it unable to run.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Cure Disease.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>5</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cure Light Wounds</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This effect restores up to 2 Body Points but never more than
      a character’s maximum. It restores an unconscious or dying
      character but does not resurrect a dead one. It inflicts 4
      Body Points of damage to undead creatures.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Cure Light Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>5</potion>
    <elixir>5</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cure Mortal Wounds</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell restores up to 30 Body Points but never more than
      a character’s maximum. It restores an unconscious or dying
      character but does not resurrect a dead one. It inflicts 60
      Body Points of damage to undead creatures.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Cure Mortal Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>40</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cure Serious Wounds</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell restores up to 10 Body Points but never more than
      a character’s maximum. It restores an unconscious or dying
      character but does not resurrect a dead one. It inflicts 20
      Body Points of damage to undead creatures.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Cure Serious Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>20</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Cure Wounds</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell restores up to 5 Body Points but never more than
      a character’s maximum. It restores an unconscious or dying
      character but does not resurrect a dead one. It inflicts 10
      Body Points of damage to undead creatures.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Cure Wounds.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>2</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>10</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Death</name>
    <group>Gift</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This effect causes the spirit of any victim with a
      metabolism to flee its body. Any armor the character was
      wearing is still intact, but all spells active on the victim
      will disappear.

      This acts as a Killing Blow, and the only thing that will
      save the victim from resurrection is a Life spell.
    </description>
    <remove>Life</remove>
    <deadline>Five minutes</deadline>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the gift of Death.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
    <elixir>45</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Desecrate</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will remain in effect as long as the subject’s
      hands are crossed over the chest and no body damage is
      taken, or ten minutes, whichever is shorter. The recipient
      is protected against all weapon attacks from living
      creatures, including arrows and bolts. It does not protect
      against Spell Strikes.

      You cannot run while affected by a Desecrate. You can not do
      anything that requires the use of your hands, such as cast
      spells, use weapons, use poisons, feed someone a potion, or
      pick up items. The only exception to this is touch casting
      on yourself or activating a magic item.

      You can be fed a potion and you can continue to hold things
      that were in your hands at the time the Desecrate began.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Desecrate you.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Destroy</name>
    <group>Summoned Force</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will utterly destroy any object up to the size of
      a normal door, rendering it useless. It cannot be used to
      create a door-sized hole in an object larger than a
      door. Once destroyed, the phys rep will become unusable but
      not unrecognizable. A Destroy cast at a door will not
      totally destroy the door, but will damage it enough to allow
      passage through the door’s frame.

      This spell can target a suit of armor and will destroy the
      armor completely. The armor cannot be refit and is ruined
      forever. The spell Shield will be unaffected.

      The spell will not work on a permanent magic item or a
      magically protected item such as a Wizard Locked
      door. Destroying a trapped item will set off and destroy the
      trap as well.

      The target item must be named, and only the target item will
      be Destroyed. Items that are contained within or attached
      will not be affected. If there are two or more items that
      fit the description of the incant, then a hand-held item
      will be affected before one simply carried on one’s person;
      thus if a caster says “I summon a force to destroy your
      weapon” then the sword that is being carried will be
      destroyed rather than the dagger strapped to the back.

      If the item that is being carried is protected against the
      Destroy (such as by being strengthened or by being a magic
      weapon), then the spell is used up and will not affect
      another similar item in the possession of the target.

      A shield is not considered a “weapon” for the purpose of
      Destroy.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I summon a force to Destroy &lt;item&gt;.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>35</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Destroy Undead</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will destroy any one lesser undead
      creature. Greater undead will take 50 Body Points of damage.

      This spell will not affect a living target, although, like
      all spells, it will remove a living person’s Spell Shield or
      Reflect Magic.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Destroy Undead.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Destruction</name>
    <group>Curse</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will cause the victim to take double damage from
      all attacks that would affect them, either physical or
      magical. This applies only to damage causing attacks; for
      instance, a Bind spell would still affect the victim
      normally.

      This effect is not cumulative; if a victim is hit by two
      Destruction spells, the second one will have no effect
      except to restart the time period before the Destruction
      expires.

      This spell will not affect a creature’s threshold or other
      defensive mechanisms, nor does it make a creature vulnerable
      to attacks that would normally not affect it.

      This effect will last for 10 minutes or until removed by a
      Remove Destruction, a Purify, or a Dispel.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <remove>Remove Destruction</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I curse you with Destruction.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>35</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Disarm</name>
    <group>Summoned Force</group>
    <duration>Five seconds</duration>
    <description>
      This spell causes the target to drop one specific hand-held
      item. The dropped item may not be picked up by the victim
      for five seconds.

      The caster decides what the item is that is to be
      disarmed. A general description like “weapon” is fine,
      although if the target is holding two items that match the
      description, it is the target’s choice as to which to
      drop. If the target is only carrying one thing, then “item”
      is sufficient.

      Shields, arrows, and bolts are not considered “weapons” for
      purposes of this spell, although a bow or crossbow is. If
      the caster wishes to disarm a shield, arrow or bolt, then
      the specific item must be stated in the verbal.

      Spell packets cannot be affected by this spell, but gas
      globes can be.

      Disarm is strong enough to overcome any rope or chain that
      may be attached to the hand.  If the chain is unshatterable
      then it will become “unrung.” You cannot avoid this spell by
      tying your weapon to your hand.

      If a Paste of Stickiness was applied to the item up to ten
      minutes prior, the item will remain in your hand, but the
      Paste of Stickiness will be used up in the process. The
      Paste of Stickiness tag must be taped to the item. The
      proper call to use in this circumstance is “no effect.”

      A Spirit Linked item will not be dropped, but cannot be used
      for five seconds. The victim must place the weapon behind
      his or her back for the five seconds.

      You cannot avoid this spell by borrowing a weapon and thus
      claiming that the spell doesn’t affect you because the
      weapon isn’t “yours.”  Nor can you avoid it by dropping the
      weapon to the ground or throwing your weapon up in the air
      just before the packet is about to hit you, thus claiming
      that the weapon was not in your possession at the point of
      contact of the spell.
    </description>
    <prevent>Paste of Stickiness</prevent>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I summon a force to Disarm your &lt;item&gt;.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>5</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Disease</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will infect the recipient with a debilitating
      disease. The infection is not contagious, but makes the
      victim unable to run.

      Against undead, this spell will remove the effects of a Cure
      Disease spell.

      This spell might not be effective against creatures without
      a metabolism.
    </description>
    <remove>Cure Disease</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to cause Disease.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>5</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Dispel</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This effect will dispel all active effects on a given
      creature or object whatever the cause, whether beneficial or
      harmful.

      It will not remove Wards, Circles of Power, or anything from
      the Greater Command effects group (Amnesia, Love Potion #9,
      Enslavement, Euphoria or Terror) with the exception that it
      will remove the effect of Amnesia if administered within the
      first ten minutes.

      Dispel will remove Wizard Locks, Walls of Force, and
      Prisons.

      A Dispel thrown at a person will not remove effects on any
      items held by that person.  For instance, Belthivis is hit
      by a Dispel. All of his spell protectives are now
      gone. However, the Weakness Weapon Coating he has on his
      dagger is still active.

      A Dispel thrown at a caster will not stop already existing
      effects of that caster’s spell.  For example: Darlissa casts
      a Shun at a goblin. She is then hit with a Dispel. All
      active spells on her are now gone, but the Shun is still in
      effect.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power to Dispel.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>40</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Dominate</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect makes the victim subject to specific commands of
      the person who administered the effect. For the elixir, it
      would be the person who administered the elixir, which would
      include placing it within food or drink, even if that person
      is not in view at the time.

      The target of a Dominate will not attack the person who
      administered the Dominate while it is in effect.

      The administrator can give the target multiple commands
      within the ten minute period, but the victim will only
      follow the last one given.

      While following these commands the target is in a trance and
      performs the last order until that order has been
      completed. Afterward the target will stand and await the
      next order.

      After ten minutes (or after the effect is countered), the
      victim comes out of the trance and acts as normal, and has
      full knowledge that he or she was dominated and what was
      done during that time.

      While dominated, the victim must perform actions to the best
      of his or her ability and knowledge, including the use of
      spells and skills. The victim does not have the ability to
      pick and choose less effective abilities to use, nor may
      they choose to not perform certain commands due to their
      personality or race. For example, if the victim knows that
      the person who Dominated them is undead, and that person
      commands the victim to heal them, they will not only cast
      necromancy on that person but will not be able to choose to
      use less powerful spells if they have more powerful ones
      available that are needed. Similarly, if a Flame Elemental
      Dominated someone, and that character knew that Flame
      Elementals are healed by Flame, they would do their best to
      use Flame to heal the Elemental if commanded.

      The victim can defend themselves from any attackers, but if
      the caster attacks the victim the Dominate effect ends.

      This effect can be removed by an Awaken, a Break Command, a
      Dispel, or a Purify. Note as well that only one Command
      effect may be active on the victim at any one time. The most
      recent Command effect takes precedence. This spell is not
      strong enough to override any Greater Command effect such as
      Enslavement.

      The death of the administrator will not necessarily end the
      Dominate. For instance, Darlissa is Dominated to Vorin who
      commands her to heal him. She stands behind him and throws
      healing into him as he needs it in battle.  Vorin is killed
      by Rendal, and Darlissa immediately throws a Life spell at
      Vorin and then heals him up. Vorin’s death did not stop the
      Domination.

      This spell only works on creatures that have a mind as
      defined by the game. Many creatures (such as lesser undead,
      golems or insects) do not have a mind that can be affected
      by this effect.

      The only valid commands that a caster can give a target
      while they are dominated are listed below. Note that the
      wording of a command does not need to exactly match the
      following but it should be similar enough to it so that the
      target can understand what is meant.

      Defend me: The target must protect the caster from all
      attacks to the best of their ability, even if it requires
      using spells and magic items. During this time, the target
      will not attack anyone who is not attacking them or the
      caster.

      Follow me: The target must follow the caster. The target
      will not attack anyone who is not attacking them.

      Give your &lt;item&gt; to me: The target must give the named
      item to the caster.

      Heal me: The target must make every attempt to heal or Life
      the caster. During this time the target will not attack
      anyone and will do everything possible, including fighting
      their allies, to prevent the healing from being stopped.

      Return to normal: This command ends the Dominate effect.
    </description>
    <remove>Awaken</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>35</elixir>
    <gas>40</gas>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Dragon's Breath</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the caster to throw a bolt of magical
      flame which inflicts 40 points of fire damage to the
      victim. The flame is eldritch in origin and will not
      otherwise set anything alight.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth a Dragon's Breath.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>40</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Drain</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect will introduce impurities into the victim’s
      blood. The victim is left extremely weak, and unable to
      fight or move faster than normal walking speed. The victim
      becomes unable to use any Game Abilities.

      It can be removed by a Purify or a Dispel or by the death of
      the victim.

      If this spell is cast upon an undead creature, it will have
      the same effect as a Purify has on a living creature. In
      this capacity, Drain will remove Healing effects instead of
      Necromancy effects.

      It may be ineffective on certain creatures that have no
      metabolism.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Drain you.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>40</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Earth Blade</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the recipient to transform a weapon into a
      temporary earth-enchanted blade. The recipient chooses when
      to use the Earth Blade, and announces the total damage of
      the swing while saying “earth” instead of “normal” or
      “silver.” It may be used on any weapon, even bows and
      crossbows.

      This spell lasts until dispelled or ten minutes pass,
      whichever is first.

      Note that this spell only affects creatures who are harmed
      by earth, but does not heal those normally healed by
      earth. Since all players are not undead, they will not be
      affected by any creature calling “earth” damage. However,
      this spell will set off a Magic Armor even if the target is
      immune to the spell’s effect.

      Damage bypasses any armor on the target and does direct body
      damage.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to grant you an Earth Blade.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Earth Storm</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the caster to throw earthbased damage
      spells.

      At the time of casting, the caster plants both feet. As long
      as both feet remain planted, the verbal is stated, and the
      spell is not disrupted as per normal spell rules, the caster
      may throw packets. While the spell is in effect, the caster
      can perform no other Game Ability nor cast any other spell.

      Each packet thrown counts as a separate spell which causes
      10 points of earth damage, which goes directly into Body
      Points and is not blocked by armor. The caster must say
      “Earth Storm” with each packet thrown.

      This spell will only damage creatures who are damaged by
      earth and may not be used to heal. Undead will thus take 10
      points of damage per packet (not 20!), while most living
      creatures will not take any damage. However, like all
      spells, this spell will use up a Spell Shield or Reflect
      Magic even if the target is immune to the spell’s effect.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to summon an Earth Storm, Earth Storm, Earth Storm...</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Elemental Blade</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the recipient to transform a weapon into a
      temporary elemental-enchanted blade.

      The recipient chooses which element and when to use the
      Elemental Blade, and announces the total damage of the swing
      while saying “&lt;element&gt;” instead of “normal” or
      “silver.”

      Available choices are ice, flame, lightning, or stone. It
      may be used on any weapon, even bows and crossbows.

      This spell lasts until dispelled or ten minutes pass,
      whichever is first.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of an Elemental Blade.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Elemental Blast</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the caster to affect a target with a bolt
      of magical stone, lightning, ice, or flame, doing 45 points
      of eldritch damage.

      The caster of the spell may choose which type of damage to
      throw at the time of the casting, signifying such through
      the verbal.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth a(n) &lt;Flame, Ice, Lightning, or Stone&gt; Blast.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Elemental Shield</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This spell protects the recipient from the next effect with
      the word “elemental” in the verbal. It is then immediately
      used up.

      This spell cannot be used to protect the recipient from a
      flame or acid trap or from elemental-based Evocation spells.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of an Elemental Shield.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>30</potion>
    <scroll>30</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Endow</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This spell endows the recipient with the ability to inflict two
      extra points of damage if the swing hits the target.

      The total damage must be announced while swinging.

      Once called, the spell is used up whether the blow succeeds or
      not.

      The recipient may choose when to use an Endow.

      An Endow will also allow a recipient to break free, or to break
      someone else free, from an Entangle. However, doing so immediately
      expends the benefit of the spell. You must state “Endow, I break you
      free” when doing so. This is an out-of-game statement and can be made
      while under the effects of Silence.

      This spell can also be used to perform certain limited
      role-playing tasks such as quickly dragging an unconscious or
      debilitated creature for five seconds without having to literally
      perform the task out-of-game. You must state “Endow” when doing these
      actions. This is an out-of-game statement and can be made while under
      the effects of Silence.

      Endow does not allow you to break a lock or other item, throw
      creatures, break down doors, or jump long distances. It does not allow
      you to hurt a monster that can only be damaged by magical weapons.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of an Endow.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>5</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Enflame</name>
    <group>Summoned Force</group>
    <duration>Five seconds</duration>
    <description>
      This effect causes any hand-held item to flare with painful
      magic, causing 20 points of damage to the person or creature
      carrying the item. It will also act as a Disarm effect
      towards that item if the creature is affected by the
      damage. Since this effect is in the Summoned Force effect
      group, only defences against Summoned Force are applicable.

      If you are not holding a hand-held item, then this spell
      will do no damage to you (although, like all spells, it will
      remove your Spell Shield or activate a Reflect Magic). Claws
      are not considered a hand-held item.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I summon a force to Enflame &lt;item&gt;.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Enslavement</name>
    <group>Greater Command</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      The victim of this effect is enslaved to the person
      administering the effect and obeys absolutely any and all commands
      given by the person to whom they are enslaved.

      If administered by a poison, the victim will be enslaved to
      whoever did the poisoning, even if that person is not in view at the
      time.

      The victim will even commit suicide, cast necromancy, or
      otherwise act out of character in pursuit of the commands.

      An enslaved person will never attack the person who enslaved
      them unless ordered by the enslaver to do so.

      If enslaved and given an order through a Charm, Dominate, or
      through any other effect which contradicts an order given by the
      enslaver, the Enslavement will always take precedence. If there is no
      conflict then the enslaved victim must still obey all rules of other
      controlling magics. The most recent Enslavement effect takes
      precedence if there is a conflict.

      You cannot be enslaved to ignore other effects; in other words,
      the enslaver cannot order you to never be affected by Fears or
      Dominates or Intoxicates or any other effect that would normally
      affect you. The victim continues to obey the commands until
      cured. Enslavement can only be removed by the specific antidote or
      through resurrection.

      Characters cured of Enslavement will remember having been
      enslaved. This does not override any applicable Amnesia effects.
    </description>
    <remove>Enslavement Antidote</remove>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Enslavement Antidote</name>
    <group>Remove Greater Command</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This antidote is the only thing that releases a victim from
      the effects of an Enslavement effect other than
      resurrection.

      It will not remove role-playing-only biata or stone elf
      mental affects.
    </description>
    <elixir>45</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Entangle</name>
    <group>Binding</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      Some monsters can shoot a substance that uses a physical
      means to trap victims (such as sticky strands of silk). The
      effect of this is like the effect Web except that it is not
      normally magical in any way. Unless otherwise specified by
      an explicit delivery type, it is entirely a physical effect
      and as such is not stopped by any Spell Protections.

      An Oil of Slipperiness applied to the body less than ten
      minutes beforehand will protect against one such attack.

      A Release spell, an Alchemical Solvent, or an Oil of
      Slipperiness will free a victim. It can also be removed by a
      Dispel. A Purify will not release the victim, as this is not
      an effect on the spirit.

      The victim can be cut by someone using an edged weapon, but
      this takes at least three seconds (“One I cut you out, two I
      cut you out, three I cut you out.”).

      You can use an Endow to break free, expending the spell or
      skill in the process. Someone else with an Endow effect can
      likewise break you free.
    </description>
    <prevent>Oil of Slipperiness</prevent>
    <remove>Alchemical Solvent</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Edged Weapon</remove>
    <remove>Endow</remove>
    <remove>Oil of Slipperiness</remove>
    <remove>Release</remove>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Euphoria</name>
    <group>Greater Command</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This elixir is highly addictive. It gives the victim a
      feeling of euphoria that lasts about an hour. Any time the
      addicted character does not get one dose of Euphoria in a 24
      hour period, one Body Point is temporarily deducted from
      that character’s maximum Body Points.

      The 24 hour period is calculated from the time of the
      initial ingestion of the Euphoria elixir.

      This maximum Body Point deduction cannot be cured as long as
      the person is still under the effects of the drug. The
      cumulative maximum Body point deduction damage will not take
      place between events or at events not attended.

      A victim who reaches -1 Body Points will die, needing a
      resurrection (a Life spell will not work, as their maximum
      Body Point total is still -1).

      The grip of Euphoria can only be broken if the character is
      given the specific antidote, or by resurrection. Receiving
      the Antidote will allow for healing up to the victim’s
      maximum amount of Body Points before the Euphoria.
    </description>
    <remove>Euphoria Antidote</remove>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Euphoria Antidote</name>
    <group>Remove Greater Command</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This antidote is the only thing other than resurrection that
      releases a victim of Euphoria.  It will restore the victim’s
      normal Body Point maximum but does not cure any Body Points
      lost during the addiction.
    </description>
    <elixir>45</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Fear</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      Some creatures have the ability to invoke a magical fear.

      The feared victim must attempt to break Line of Sight and
      cannot perform any Game Abilities while trying to escape.

      If breaking Line of Sight is impossible, the victim will
      stay as far from the attacker as possible. Even if Line of
      Sight is broken, the effect lasts ten minutes or until the
      creature is dead.

      For example, Ena gets Feared by a vampire. She runs
      screaming around a corner and five seconds later (as per the
      “Line of Sight” rule), she feels calm again. She reaches
      into her pouch to pull out an Awaken potion but the vampire
      then appears around the corner. Ena is once more feared to
      the point where she can do nothing but run screaming again,
      trying to break Line of Sight, as the ten minutes are not
      up.

      The racial abilities Resist Command and Resist Fear can be
      used as a defense against this ability and an Awaken, Dispel
      or Purify will free someone who is Feared. The fear can also
      be broken by a Break Command.

      Note as well that only one Command effect may be active on
      the victim at any one time, and the most recent Command
      effect takes precedence.
    </description>
    <remove>Awaken</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Feeblemind</name>
    <group>Alteration</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect lowers a character’s intelligence to that of an
      idiot for ten minutes.

      A Feebleminded person is still smart enough to run away from
      obvious danger but too stupid to use any Game Abilities
      (even Read and Write) or use potions, scrolls, elixirs or
      magic items.

      A Feebleminded person can never take actions to cure the
      Feeblemind. It can be removed by an Antidote, a Dispel, or a
      Purify.
    </description>
    <remove>Antidote</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>30</elixir>
    <gas>35</gas>
    <weapon>40</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Flame Bolt</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 20 points of eldritch flame damage to the victim.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth a Flame Bolt.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>20</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Fortress</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell provides its target with limited immunity to
      weapon attacks. The spell will last ten minutes or until the
      target breaks the spell’s physical requirements.

      The target of the spell must plant his or her feet and raise
      both arms above the head without crossing them. Moving
      either foot or lowering an arm ends the spell.

      Any body damage taken also breaks the Fortress.

      The target may touch-cast spells (on themselves only) but
      may use no other Game Abilities without breaking the
      protections of the Fortress.

      While the Fortress lasts, the target is immune to weapon
      blows of 10 or less.

      For example: Belthivis finds himself surrounded by
      undead. He holds his hands over his head and casts a
      Fortress. An undead hits him for “9 Death” and Belthivis
      says “no effect” because it is less than his Protection Aura
      of 10. Another undead hits him for “11 normal” but that only
      affects his armor, and so the Fortress is still
      active. Belthivis touch-casts an Armor spell and a Spell
      Shield on himself while still in the Fortress. After ten
      minutes the Fortress will expire if he does not lower it
      himself or take any body damage.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I build a Fortress.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Hallucinate</name>
    <group>Alteration</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This alchemical substance causes the victim to
      hallucinate. They will see pink elephants and other strange
      things for ten minutes. The victim will probably be aware
      that they are under the effects of a poison but will be
      unable to do much about it.

      Hallucinate is a role-play effect which affects all of the
      user’s perceptions, not just their sight. A blindfold might
      block out visual hallucinations (or it might not), but it
      would not block out the character’s other senses, which are
      also affected by the Hallucinate.

      When under its effects, Game Abilities can be used, but the
      player will most likely use them against imaginary
      creatures, and may even read potion labels and scrolls
      incorrectly in their delirium.

      It can be removed by an Antidote, a Dispel, or a Purify.
    </description>
    <remove>Antidote</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>10</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Harm Undead</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 20 Body Points of damage to an undead
      creature.

      This spell will not affect a living target, although it will
      remove a living creature’s Spell Shield or Reflect Magic.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Harm Undead.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Help Undead</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will heal an undead creature for 20 Body Points
      of damage.

      This spell will not affect a living target, although it will
      remove a living creature’s Spell Shield or Reflect Magic.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Help Undead.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Ice Bolt</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 15 points of eldritch cold damage to the
      victim.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth an Ice Bolt.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>15</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Ice Storm</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>p
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 35 points of eldritch cold damage to the
      victim.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth an Ice Storm.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>35</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Intoxicate</name>
    <group>Alteration</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This acts as a strong alcoholic drink yet is odorless and
      tasteless. It will render the victim quite drunk and will
      affect all characters and races, even those that for
      role-playing reasons are “immune” to alcohol. It can be
      removed by an Antidote, a Dispel, or a Purify.
    </description>
    <remove>Antidote</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>5</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Laugh</name>
    <group>Alteration</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect will cause the victim to laugh and giggle
      repeatedly for ten minutes, during which time no Game
      Abilities can be used.

      The victim can still run from the area and can still speak
      between giggles and thus call for help, activate a magic
      item, or drink an Antidote.

      It will affect all characters, even stone elves. It can be
      removed by an Antidote, a Dispel, or a Purify.
    </description>
    <remove>Antidote</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>20</elixir>
    <gas>25</gas>
    <weapon>30</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Lesser Investment</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Five days</duration>
    <description>
      This spell must be cast by a caster who is invested in a
      Ward or Wizard Lock. While inside that Ward or Wizard Lock,
      the caster may use this spell to invest others into the Ward
      or Wizard Lock. Any who are inside when the spell is cast
      are invested and may enter and leave at will or recognize
      others into the Ward or Wizard Lock.

      In no event will this spell last longer than the Ward or
      Wizard Lock to which the person is invested. If a Ward is
      created on Day 1 and a Lesser Investment is cast on Day 4,
      both will expire on Day 5.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I build a Lesser Investment.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>15</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Life</name>
    <group>Gift</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell must be cast within five minutes of a creature’s
      death. It restores the creature to one Body Point and the
      creature is not forced to resurrect. Only this spell can
      save someone who has been given a Killing Blow or hit by a
      Death effect.

      This spell will not normally affect a living target or an
      undead creature, nor a permanently dead character. Like all
      spells, it will remove a living person or undead creature’s
      Spell Shield or Reflect Magic.

      This spell must be cast upon the player’s body to be
      effective. Once the spell is cast, the entire body reforms
      and any parts elsewhere will dissipate.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the gift of Life.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Light</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Five days</duration>
    <description>
      This effect produces a glowing light and allows the person
      activating the effect to kindle a light wand. The light can
      then be used by anyone.

      This will not work without a phyical representation. You
      cannot cast a Light spell at a person or tree and have the
      person or tree glow.  There must be a flashlight or other
      out-of-game light source provided.

      If using a flashlight for this spell, the lens of the
      flashlight must be covered by a cloth, tissue paper or a gel
      to diffuse the light. Do not shine the light in anyone’s
      face.

      This spell (like all spells) will remove a Spell Shield or
      Reflect Magic.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I build a Light.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>5</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Light Vorpal Coating</name>
    <group>Coating</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      Putting this contact gel on a weapon makes the weapon
      inflict 2 extra points of damage once for the very next
      strike.

      The tag must be taped to the weapon.

      This cannot be combined with any other weapon contact gel
      such as other vorpal coatings.
    </description>
    <remove>Alchemical Solvent</remove>
    <weapon>5</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Lightning Bolt</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 10 points of eldritch lightning damage
      to the victim.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth a Lightning Bolt.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>2</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>10</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Lightning Storm</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 30 points of eldritch lightning damage
      to the victim.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth a Lightning Storm.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>30</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Liquid Light</name>
    <group>Coating</group>
    <duration>Until daybreak</duration>
    <description>
      This substance will allow for the use of a cyalume light
      stick or other light phys rep to be used in-game.

      It lasts until daybreak or until the phys rep stops working,
      whichever is shorter. It cannot be applied to a tree or
      other object to make it glow.
    </description>
    <remove>Alchemical Solvent</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <contact>5</contact>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Love</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This causes the victim to fall deeply in love with the next
      member of the appropriate sex seen.

      The victim will not act out of character while in love; he
      or she may flirt, ask the new love out for a romantic
      dinner, write bad poetry, or perhaps merely pine away from a
      distance. This potion is not an aphrodisiac.

      It lasts ten minutes and like all Command effects can be
      resisted by a Resist Command or Resist Poison and removed by
      a Break Command or an Awaken, Antidote or Purify.

      Note as well that only one Command effect may be active on
      the victim at any one time, and the most recent Command
      effect takes precedence.
    </description>
    <remove>Antidote</remove> <!-- Love is not Alteration -->
    <remove>Awaken</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove> <!-- Replace Antidote -->
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>15</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Love Potion #9</name>
    <group>Greater Command</group>
    <duration>Five days</duration>
    <description>
      This potion acts the same as the regular Love Poison except
      that it cannot be cured or resisted. It will expire on its
      own in five days or upon resurrection.
    </description>
    <elixir>45</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Magic Armor</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will protect the wearer from the next single
      weapon strike. The recipient must state “Magic Armor.”

      The attack and the Magic Armor are then expended.

      This does not protect against a Killing Blow or a fall, nor
      does it work against any traps other than weapon traps.

      A Magic Armor will be used even if the amount of damage
      called is “zero.”
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of a Magic Armor.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>2</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>10</potion>
    <scroll>10</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Magic Blade</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell allows the recipient to transform a weapon into a
      temporary magic-enchanted blade, allowing damage against
      certain creatures which can only be harmed by magic. It may
      be used on any weapon, even bows and crossbows.

      The recipient announces the total damage of the swing while
      saying “magic” instead of “normal” or “silver.”
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of a Magic Blade.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Magic Storm</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <description>
      At the time of casting, the caster plants both feet. As long as both
      feet remain planted, the verbal is stated, and the spell is not
      disrupted as per normal spell rules, the caster may throw
      packets. While the spell is in effect, the caster can perform no other
      skill nor cast any other spell.

      Each packet thrown counts as a separate spell which causes 10 points
      of damage. The caster must say “Magic Storm” with each packet thrown.

      Like all spells, this spell will use up a Spell Shield or Reflect
      Magic even if the target is immune to the spell’s effect.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth a Magic Storm, Magic Storm, Magic Storm...</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Nausea</name>
    <group>Alteration</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This elixir will cause the victim to be violently ill for
      ten minutes, during which time no Game Abilities can be
      used. The victim can walk slowly from the area and can still
      speak between heaves and thus call for help, drink an elixir
      or potion, or activate a magic item. It can be removed by an
      Antidote, Dispel, or a Purify.
    </description>
    <remove>Antidote</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>25</elixir>
    <gas>30</gas>
    <weapon>35</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Oil of Slipperiness</name>
    <group>Coating</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      When this contact gel is placed on an item no larger than a
      weapon, it prevents that item from being held for ten
      minutes from the time the item is first touched. This can be
      counteracted by an Alchemical Solvent or a Paste of
      Stickiness. If placed upon the body or clothing, this
      substance will resist one Entangle attack, after which it
      will be expended.

      For example: Terin is getting ready to go into a battle
      against giant spiders. He is aware that they can throw
      entangles, so he takes out his Oil of Slipperiness and
      applies it to himself. This is represented by taking the
      tag, ripping off the “unused” flag. He runs into battle and
      is hit by an entangle. “Resist,” he replies.  The Oil is now
      used up so any other such attacks will affect him as normal.

      Note that this will not protect against a Pin, Bind, Web, or
      Confine spell.
    </description>
    <remove>Alchemical Solvent</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Paste of Stickiness</remove>
    <contact>15</contact>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Paralysis</name>
    <group>Curse</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect completely immobilizes the victim. The target
      cannot move any part of their body and may be given a
      Killing Blow while thus trapped.

      This can be removed by a Remove Paralysis, a Dispel or a
      Purify. A Release spell will not remove the effect.

      This spell only works on creatures that have a metabolism.

      Some creatures, such as undead, golems or some elementals,
      are not affected by this spell.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <remove>Remove Paralysis</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I curse you with Paralysis.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <elixir>40</elixir>
    <gas>45</gas>
  </effect>

  <effects>
    <name>Paranoia</name>
    <group>Alteration</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This causes the victim to think that everyone is conspiring
      and plotting against them.  Players should react as they
      think their characters would to this “knowledge.” Paranoia
      will never force a player to cast necromancy or otherwise
      act out of their true nature.

      It can be removed by an Antidote, Dispel, or a Purify.
    </description>
    <remove>Antidote</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>5</elixir>
    <gas>10</gas>
    <weapon>15</weapon>
  </effects>
  
  <effect>
    <name>Paste of Stickiness</name>
    <group>Coating</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      When this contact gel is placed on an item no larger than a
      weapon, it causes anyone touching it for more than three seconds to
      become stuck to it for ten minutes.

      This can be counteracted by an Oil of Slipperiness, an
      Alchemical Solvent, or a Release spell.

      A Killing Blow will not remove this effect but a resurrection
      obviously will.

      If placed upon a weapon or item, this substance will resist one
      Disarm or Enflame attack, after which it will be expended.

      For example: Terin is getting ready to go into a battle, so he
      places a Paste of Stickiness on his weapon. This is represented by
      taking the tag, ripping off the “unused” flag. Terin runs into battle
      and is hit by a Disarm spell.  “Resist,” he replies. The Paste of
      Stickiness is now used up, so the next Disarm spell will affect him as
      normal.

      A victim hit with an Enflame spell will still say “resist” to
      the disarming magics of the spell but will still take the physical
      damage from the spell.

      If used on a weapon and the weapon is destroyed or shattered,
      the holder will be stuck with the weapon’s pommel in his or her hand
      for the duration of the Paste of Stickiness and cannot hold anything
      else in that hand during that time. Out-of-game, you should drop your
      weapon phys rep but hold your hand in a fist for the remainder of the
      ten minutes.
    </description>
    <remove>Alchemical Solvent</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Oil of Slipperiness</remove>
    <remove>Release</remove>
    <contact>15</contact>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Pin</name>
    <group>Binding</group>
    <duration>Line-of-sight</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will instantly root the target’s right foot in
      place. If the target’s foot was off the ground at the time
      the packet hit, then the foot will be forced to the
      ground. The target may pivot their body 360 degrees but may
      not move their right foot.

      It can be removed by a Dispel, a Purify, or a Release.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <remove>Release</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With mystic force I Pin you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>2</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>10</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Poison Shield</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This effect protects the recipient from the next attack with
      the word “poison” in the verbal. It is then immediately used
      up. It will not protect against ingested elixirs, Weapon
      Coatings, or Contact Gels such as Oils of Slipperiness or
      Pastes of Stickiness.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of a Poison Shield.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
    <elixir>20</elixir>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Prison</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell seals the victim into a rigid, form-fitting and
      unbreakable barrier, trapping him or her within. The victim
      cannot move, speak, or perform any Game Abilities, including
      High Magic abilities.

      It lasts for ten minutes, but may be dropped by the caster
      at any time if he or she touches the victim and states
      “Prison down.” This statement is out-of-game, and can be
      used even if the caster is Silenced or inside the
      Prison. Any observers who hear the statement are aware that
      the Prison was dropped, and might know who dropped it.

      A Dispel will bring down the Prison, but will not dispel any
      other effects on the creature inside.

      Any creature sealed within a Prison will call “No effect” to
      all effects (except Dispel and the Massive carrier), nor
      will they take any damage from physical attacks or
      traps. Healing Arts or First Aid will not work through a
      Prison. A creature within a Prison cannot be searched.

      No Game Abilities, including High Magic abilities, may be
      used while under a Prison effect.

      However, the Prison does not provide complete and absolute
      protection against harm.  The victim will suffocate if
      placed underwater (assuming the victim needs to breathe to
      survive). The Prisoned creature may also be injured or slain
      from overwhelming damage such as falling from a great
      height, at the judgement of a Marshal or Plot member on the
      scene.

      A Vampire Charm or other gaze attack will still work
      provided the Prisoned creature’s eyes were open at the time
      the Prison was cast.

      As with a Ward, no gasses other than air can get inside. The
      barrier is not a frictionless surface, and has as much
      friction as a normal creature.

      A victim of the Prison is completely aware of his or her
      surroundings and unless unconscious or otherwise impaired
      will remember all that occurred while Prisoned.

      Only the caster may deliver a Killing Blow to the
      recipient. The caster must say “Prison Down” after
      delivering a Killing Blow. (“Killing Blow one, Killing Blow
      two, Killing Blow three, Prison Down.”) If the Killing Blow
      fails (for example, the creature inside is immune to the
      caster’s attack), then the Prison will drop as soon as the
      Killing Blow is completed and the creature may then defend
      itself.

      A Killing Blow delivered with the Massive carrier will still
      take a Prison down, whether it succeeds or not, and whether
      performed by the caster of the Prison or not.

      For safety reasons, you are never allowed to lay the
      Prisoned victim on the ground, remove the Prison, and then
      beat the victim to -1 points.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I build a Prison.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Purify</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This effect will remove all harmful effects from the spirit,
      leaving protectives. “Harmful effects” includes everything
      in the effects groups Alteration, Binding, Command, Curse,
      and Necromancy.

      It will not remove effects in the Greater Command group even
      though those effects are on the spirit. It will not cure any
      damage previously wrought by any effect.

      Purify will not remove effects that are not on the spirit
      (such as Entangle, Prison, Wizard Lock, or Walls of Force).

      This spell will affect an undead as a Drain affects the
      living. It is also a very good in-game cure for an in-game
      hangover.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Purify you.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>40</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Quicksilver</name>
    <group>Coating</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      Putting this contact gel on a weapon makes the weapon
      inflict silver damage once for the very next strike. The
      damage call is “&lt;damage&gt; silver.”
    </description>
    <remove>Alchemical Solvent</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <weapon>10</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Reflect Magic</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This effect will reflect the next effect delivered by the
      “spell” qualifier cast at the recipient back upon the
      caster, after which it is used up. The recipient must say
      “Reflect Magic” to inform the caster that the spell was
      returned.

      This spell lasts until used or Dispelled, and cannot be used
      in conjunction with a Spell Shield. If you have a Reflect
      Magic active, you may still “accept” spells that are
      touch-cast.

      When you Reflect, Bane, or Riposte an effect that has
      already been Reflected, Baned, or Riposted, the target of
      the effect is once again the original target. You may never
      Reflect, Bane, or Riposte an effect more than once from the
      same effect.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of a Reflect Magic.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>40</potion>
    <scroll>40</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Release</name>
    <group>Binding</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will release a creature caught in a Bind, Pin,
      Web, or Confine effect as well as negating all active Paste
      of Stickiness effects upon the creature. It will not free
      someone under the effects of a Paralysis or a Prison.

      This spell will remove all active binding effects, including
      Entangle, as well as handcuffs, ropes, stocks, etc.

      It will not unlock a door.

      A Hold can be called if you are physically tied up and need
      time to remove the item constricting you.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With mystic force I Release you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>5</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>25</potion>
    <scroll>25</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Remove Destruction</name>
    <group>Remove Curse</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will cancel all Destruction effects.

      It will not restore any lost Body Points.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I rid you of Destruction.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>35</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Remove Paralysis</name>
    <group>Remove Curse</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will cancel all Paralysis effects.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I rid you of Paralysis.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>40</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Remove Silence</name>
    <group>Remove Curse</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will cancel all active Silence effects.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I rid you of Silence.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>5</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>25</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Remove Weakness</name>
    <group>Remove Curse</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will cancel all active Weakness effects.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I rid you of Weakness.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>15</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Repel</name>
    <group>Binding</group>
    <duration>Concentration</duration>
    <description>
      This spell requires the caster to hit a target with a spell
      packet and hold the hand used to throw the packet palm out,
      facing the recipient. The victim and the target should then
      stay at least ten feet apart while the spell is in effect,
      and the caster must keep the hand held out toward the
      target.

      The outstretched hand cannot be used for any other purpose,
      although the caster may use the other hand for in-game
      skills.

      When the spell is first cast, the recipient must move ten
      feet away from the caster. After that, neither the recipient
      nor the caster may approach within ten feet of each other;
      the caster cannot approach the recipient any easier than the
      recipient may approach the caster. Either could back away.

      If the victim is within ten feet when the spell is cast, the
      victim must move away, but never in a manner that will
      endanger the victim or cause direct harm to the victim. In
      other words, the victim cannot be made to jump off a cliff
      or walk towards a magical rift or do any other action which
      would cause harm.

      This spell does not create a ten foot magical circle around
      the caster which is effective only upon the victim; if the
      victim has to come closer than ten feet in order to get away
      (for example, to pull close to the caster in order to get to
      an exit), then that is permissible.

      While within that ten foot area, however, the victim can
      take no in-game actions against the caster.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With mystic force I Repel you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>2</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>10</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Restore</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell causes the target’s limbs to become restored. One
      casting of this spell can restore all affected limbs.

      This spell is also the only way short of a Life spell or a
      resurrection to restore a limb that has been severed or
      amputated, or to restore a broken hand or arm.

      When cast upon undead, it has the same affect as a Wither
      has on living victims.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Restore your limbs.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>30</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Sanctuary</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will remain in effect as long as the subject’s
      hands are clasped above the head and no body damage is
      taken, or ten minutes, whichever is shorter. The recipient
      is protected against all weapon attacks from undead
      creatures, including arrows and bolts. It does not protect
      against Spell Strikes.

      You cannot run while affected by a Sanctuary. You can not do
      anything that requires the use of your hands, such as cast
      spells, use weapons, use poisons, feed someone a potion, or
      pick up items. However, you can touch-cast on yourself or
      activate a magic item.

      You can be fed a potion and you can continue to hold things
      that were in your hands at the time the Sanctuary began.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to grant you Sanctuary.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Serious Vorpal Coating</name>
    <group>Coating</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      Putting this contact gel on a weapon makes the weapon
      inflict 10 extra points of damage once for the very next
      strike.

      The tag must be taped to the weapon.

      This cannot be combined with any other weapon contact gel
      such as other vorpal coatings.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Alchemical Solvent</remove>
    <weapon>20</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Shatter</name>
    <group>Summoned Force</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will destroy any weapon, shield or any object up to
      the size of a shield, rendering it useless. It cannot be used to
      create a shield-sized hole in an object larger than a shield. The phys
      rep will not become unrecognizable, only unusable.

      This spell can target a suit of armor and will destroy the armor
      completely if the suit’s maximum value is 20 points or less. The armor
      cannot be refit and is ruined forever. Should the armor have a maximum
      value of greater than 20 points, it will be unaffected by the Shatter
      (and the owner should call “No Effect”).

      The spell will not work on a permanent magic item or a magically
      protected item such as a Wizard Locked door.

      Shattering a trapped item will set off and destroy the trap if
      the trap was set.

      The target item must be named, and only the target item will be
      Shattered. Items that are contained within or attached will not be
      affected.

      If there are two or more items that fit the description of the
      incant, then a hand-held item will be affected before one simply
      carried on one’s person; thus if a caster says “I summon a force to
      shatter your weapon” then the sword that is being carried will be
      shattered rather than the dagger strapped to the back.

      If the item that is being carried is protected against the
      Shatter (such as by being strengthened or by being a magic weapon),
      then the spell is used up and will not affect another similar item in
      the possession of the target.

      A shield is not considered a “weapon” for the purpose of
      Shatter.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I summon a force to Shatter &lt;item&gt;.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>15</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Shield</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This spell gives the recipient 5 extra Armor Points.

      These extra points are the first Armor Points lost due to
      damage.

      This spell is not limited by Armor Point limitations. A
      scholar, for instance, can wear the maximum 15 point suit of
      armor and still have this spell active.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of a Shield.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>2</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>10</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Shun</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell causes the victim to feel great discomfort around
      the caster. The victim will not initiate attack on the
      caster while the spell is in effect, and the victim will
      immediately move at least ten feet away from the caster and
      stay at least that far away while the spell is in effect.

      If the victim is within ten feet when the spell is cast, the
      victim must move away, but never in a manner that causes
      direct harm or endangers the victim.

      In other words, the victim cannot be made to jump off a
      cliff or walk towards a magical rift or do any other action
      which would cause harm.

      This spell does not create a ten foot magical circle around
      the caster which is effective only upon the victim; it
      merely makes the victim attempt to stay at least ten feet
      away.

      If the victim has to come closer than ten feet in order to
      get away (for example, to pull close to the caster in order
      to get to an exit), then that is permissible. While within
      that ten foot area however, the victim can take no ingame
      actions against the caster.

      This spell is a Command spell and can be resisted with the
      racial ability Resist Command, and it can be cured with an
      Awaken, Dispel, Purify, or Break Command. Only one Command
      effect may be active on the victim at any one time, and the
      most recent Command effect takes precedence.
    </description>
    <remove>Awaken</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I command you to Shun me.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>20</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Silence</name>
    <group>Curse</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      The victim of this spell cannot talk, activate magical
      items, or cast any spell. The player must still call out the
      damage points his or her weapons inflict if combat ensues
      while the spell is in effect, as well as any out-of-game
      phrases such as “Reflect Magic,” “Parry” or “Prepare to
      Die.”

      The silence can be removed by either Remove Silence, Purify
      or Dispel.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <remove>Remove Silence</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I curse you with Silence.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>5</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>25</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Sleep</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell causes the target to instantly fall into a deep
      sleep. Not even strong shaking or yelling in the victim’s
      ear will rouse them from this magical sleep.

      An Awaken, Purify or Dispel will wake the victim
      immediately.

      This effect will not work on some creatures without a
      metabolism, such as undead creatures, golems, or some giant
      insects.

      This is a Command effect and can be resisted by creatures
      with a Resist Command ability and removed with a Break
      Command. Note as well that only one Command effect may be
      active on the victim at any one time, and the most recent
      Command effect takes precedence.
    </description>
    <remove>Awaken</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I command you to Sleep.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>30</potion>
    <scroll>30</scroll>
    <elixir>30</elixir>
    <gas>35</gas>
    <weapon>40</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Solidify</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell forces a gaseous form to become immediately
      solid. The creature may be able to turn gaseous again if it
      has the skill.

      This spell will not work on certain creatures who are
      gaseous normally, such as noncorporeal undead or air
      elementals.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I Solidify you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Spell Shield</name>
    <group>Protection/Enhancement</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will cancel the next effect delivered by the
      “spell” qualifier cast at the recipient, including
      beneficial spells, after which it is used up. It will also
      protect against attacks that have the word “magic” in their
      incant.

      It does not protect the recipient from a magic weapon
      blow. For example: Finther is hit by Vorin who is using a
      magical weapon.  “4 Magic” says Vorin. Finther’s Spell
      Shield will not protect him from this blow.

      You must say “Spell Shield” immediately when this spell is
      used. Spell Shield cannot be used in conjunction with a
      Reflect Magic.

      If you have a Spell Shield active, you may still accept
      spells that are touch-cast. You cannot “accept” spells that
      are thrown at you, nor can you accept spells when you are
      unconscious.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I grant you the power of a Spell Shield.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>5</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>25</potion>
    <scroll>25</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Stone Bolt</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 5 points of eldritch stone damage to the victim.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth a Stone Bolt.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>1</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>5</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Stone Storm</name>
    <group>Evocation</group>
    <duration>Instant</duration>
    <description>
      This spell inflicts 25 points of eldritch stone damage to
      the victim.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call forth a Stone Storm.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>5</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>25</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Subjugate</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect allows the control of either a golem or
      elemental who is subject to specific commands of the person
      who administered the effect: In the case of the spell, this
      would be the caster.

      The target of a Subjugate spell will not attack the person
      who administered the Subjugate while it is in effect. The
      administrator can give the target multiple commands within
      the ten minute period, but the target will only follow the
      last one given. The caster of the spell may order the target
      to stop any command once it has been given without
      explicitly ordering the target to return to normal. For
      example, a caster could order a target to “Carry that
      person,” and then “Stop carrying that person.”

      Creatures who are spirit stored in golems as defined by the
      game are also affected by the spell. This includes Player
      Characters.

      While following these commands, the target is under complete
      control of the caster and performs the last order until that
      order has been completed. Afterward the target will stand
      and await the next order.

      After ten minutes (or after the effect is countered), the
      victim comes out of the control and acts as normal, and has
      full knowledge that he or she was Subjugated and what was
      done during that time.

      While Subjugated, the victim must perform actions to the
      best of his or her ability, including the use of spells,
      skills or innate abilities. Note that this spell cannot
      force a target to cast or use items that are not in his or
      her nature or ability to use.

      The victim can defend themselves from any attackers, but if
      the caster attacks the victim, the Subjugate effect ends.

      This effect can be removed by a Dispel.  The death of the
      caster will end the spell effect.

      Only one Subjugate effect may be active on the target at any
      one time. The most recent effect takes precedence.

      Subjugate is an Eldritch Force effect, and as such does not
      counter or override any Command or Greater Command. Note as
      well that all golems are immune to Command effects.

      For instance, Belthivis has managed to have himself Spirit
      Stored into an iron golem body. He is hit with a Subjugate
      spell by his arch enemy Vorin and is ordered to guard Vorin
      and his party. Belthivis immediately does everything he can
      to comply. A member of Belthivis’ party then kills Vorin and
      the spell effect ends, freeing Belthivis.

      Greater elementals may have the ability to resist the
      effects of the Subjugate spell.

      The only valid commands that a caster can give a target
      while they are Subjugated are listed below. Note that the
      wording of a command does not need to exactly match the
      following but it should be similar enough to it so that the
      target can understand what is meant.

      Guard: The target must protect the caster or any person or
      object he is told to guard from all attacks, theft or harm
      to the best of their ability, even if it requires using
      spells, skills, magic items or innate abilities, as long as
      it doesn’t go against their nature. During this time, the
      target of the Subjugate will not move unless to protect the
      object or person they’re guarding.

      Follow: The target must follow the caster or anyone the
      caster wishes followed. The target will not attack anyone
      who is not attacking them.

      Attack: The golem or elemental will attack a chosen target
      of the caster’s choosing, even if it requires using spells,
      magic items or innate abilities. Once the target of the
      attack command is on the ground, the golem or elemental will
      not attack and will wait for its new orders.

      Carry/lift: The target will carry or lift objects and or
      people if it has the necessary strength to do so.

      Return to normal: This command ends the Subjugate effect.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I Subjugate you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>7</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Terror</name>
    <group>Greater Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      The target of a Terror effect is overwhelmed by fear and
      confusion. These emotions are so intense that the character
      will attempt to flee the area and break Line of Sight, then
      fall down and curl up with fear. The character is unable to
      make any conscious decisions, including activating magic
      items or using skills.  For all intents and purposes, they
      are helpless.

      Terror is a Greater Command effect that lasts ten
      minutes. It can be resisted only through the Resist Fear
      racial skill, and is cured only through a Break Command or
      character death.

      For Example: Terin attacks a powerful undead creature which
      throws a packet at Terin with the call “Arcane Terror.”
      Terin is defenseless against this attack and runs away
      screaming until he can no longer see the undead
      creature. Terin then falls to the ground moaning,
      role-playing the intense fear his character has been gripped
      by. After ten minutes, he will come to his senses.
    </description>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Turn Undead</name>
    <group>Healing</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell will affect one lesser undead creature, causing
      it to run from the caster as if affected by Fear (see page
      118). The undead will immediately attempt to break Line of
      Sight and can use no Game Abilities while trying to escape.

      If breaking Line of Sight is impossible, the undead will
      stay as far away from the caster as possible. Even if Line
      of Sight is broken, the effect lasts ten minutes or until
      the creature (or caster) is dead. The undead will defend
      itself if cornered and unable to escape.

      A Dispel or Control Undead will rid the creature of this
      spell, allowing it to return. One casting of Control Undead
      will remove all Turn Undead effects.

      Greater undead are not affected by this spell in the same
      manner, although they will be affected as if a Shun were
      cast at them.

      This spell will not affect a living target, although it will
      remove any creature’s Spell Shield or Reflect Magic.
    </description>
    <remove>Control Undead</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon the earth to Turn Undead.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>4</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Vampire Charm</name>
    <group>Command</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      A creature with this ability can charm a person if they can
      maintain eye contact for five seconds. This power does not
      require body contact.

      It may also be delivered by other means as well (for
      example, it could be packet delivered).

      If you are charmed by such a creature, then you must obey
      all commands the creature gives you. These commands are
      absolute and are much more powerful than a Charm spell;
      instead, it is comparable to an Enslavement. If a vampire
      tells you to commit suicide, you will do so
      unquestioningly. If you are asked to cast necromancy, you
      will.

      Spell defenses will not stop a Vampire Charm; however, the
      racial skill Resist Command will protect the character from
      this effect and the skill Break Command will remove it, as
      will Awaken, Dispel, and Purify.

      Unless stated differently on the monster card, the effect
      lasts ten minutes. The vampire can renew the Vampire Charm
      within that period.

      Only one Command effect may be active on the victim at any
      one time. The most recent Command effect takes precedence.
    </description>
    <remove>Awaken</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Vertigo</name>
    <group>Alteration</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect will cause the victim to lose balance and be
      unable to remain standing for ten minutes, during which the
      victim can not use any Game Abilities.

      The victim can still speak and thus call for help or
      activate a magic item but cannot walk away. It can be
      removed by an Antidote, Dispel, or a Purify.
    </description>
    <remove>Antidote</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <elixir>30</elixir>
    <gas>35</gas>
    <weapon>40</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Vorpal Coating</name>
    <group>Coating</group>
    <duration>Indefinite</duration>
    <description>
      Putting this contact gel on a weapon makes the weapon
      inflict 5 extra points of damage once for the very next
      strike. The tag must be taped to the weapon.

      This cannot be combined with any other weapon contact gel
      such as other vorpal coatings.
    </description>
    <remove>Alchemical Solvent</remove>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <weapon>15</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Wall of Force</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This spell creates an invisible barrier that will stretch no
      more than ten feet across. This spell must be cast on a
      doorway or other portal of up to ten feet across and 25 feet
      high.

      The floor of the Wall of Force must be marked in some way
      (such as by a rope, chalk mark, or ribbon) to indicate to
      all observers that a Wall of Force is in place.

      Once the Wall of Force has been cast, the physical
      representation cannot be moved. Neither the Wall nor the
      frame may be Destroyed or Shattered. Normal traps will not
      affect it.

      Nothing may pass though the Wall once the Wall is cast,
      including spells, thrown gasses, weapons and creatures. Air
      may pass through, but other gasses may not. A gaze attack
      such as a Vampire Charm can be effective through a Wall, as
      will a Gypsy Curse.

      The wall will last for ten minutes, but may be dropped by
      the caster at any time if he or she touches the phys rep and
      states “Wall down.”  This statement is out-of-game, although
      any observers who hear the statement are aware that the wall
      was dropped, and they might know who dropped it.

      The Wall will also drop if hit by a Dispel.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I build a Wall.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>15</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Ward</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Five days</duration>
    <description>
      This spell magically seals a single room or an entire
      building. The object so affected must be an actual unmovable
      structure such as a building, a tent, or an unmovable wagon.

      When the spell is cast, a magic barrier will then appear
      enclosing the area. All portals into the area are sealed by
      the barrier, including windows.

      Nothing may enter or leave except for air itself. No gaseous
      forms, gases, weapons, spells —nothing.

      This spell allows only one portal into the structure when
      cast by a single caster. To indicate the presence of a Ward
      and the location of any portals, a large “W” must be placed
      on each portal which allows access in and out of the Ward.

      A Ward may be enhanced by multiple simultaneous
      castings. These castings must be performed by separate
      individuals and the spells cast at the same time. When
      multiple casters are involved in a Ward, the spell is
      affected in two different ways. First, each caster beyond
      the first may designate an additional portal through which
      the Ward may be accessed, using the same rules as for the
      initial portal. Second, additional casters will increase the
      size of the Ward as follows: A single Ward may cover a
      building up to the size of a small home or large
      cabin. Larger buildings, as determined by the local
      chapter’s staff, may require multiple Wards to be cast to
      cover the entire building.  Players are encouraged to check
      with their local staff beforehand to determine if multiple
      Wards will be required. You cannot mix a Ward with a Wizard
      Lock in this fashion.

      The “W” must be placed on the portal prior to casting this
      spell, and this must be performed in-game. Any observers
      will thus be aware that you are attempting to place a Ward
      or a Wizard Lock on the building.

      As soon as the spell is cast, the names of the persons who
      are invested must be written on the marshal’s notes attached
      to the back of the door.

      All persons within the Ward when it is cast are invested
      into the Ward. They may then enter and leave the Warded
      building at any time while the Ward is in effect. Once the
      Ward is cast, an invested member can, within the 5 days,
      cast Lesser Investment to invest other people into the Ward.

      In order to allow others to pass into or out of the Ward,
      they must be “recognized” by an invested member of the
      Ward. The invested member must clearly gesture, touch, or
      name the subject creature and must state “the Ward
      recognizes you.” This is an out-of-game statement, so it can
      be made while Silenced. The effect is understood in-game by
      all who hear it.

      Upon being recognized, a person must immediately enter or
      exit the Ward. If the recognized person does not immediately
      act upon the recognition, then the recognition will expire.

      Invested members who are unconscious (or conscious, yet
      unwilling) will not pass through the Ward unless recognized
      by someone else.

      When using combat skills or spells, you must be completely
      inside or outside of the Ward. For example, you cannot begin
      a spell incant while inside the Ward, and then step out and
      throw your packet.

      If the Ward is somehow destroyed and replaced with a new
      one, an out-of-game notice must be placed upon the Marshal’s
      Notes on the door.

      It is possible to Ward or Wizard Lock a smaller room within
      the Ward as long as the two rooms do not share the same
      portal. The outer Ward or Wizard Lock must be cast first.

      Wards are not affected by Dispel. The only way to remove a
      Ward is through ritual magic.

      The only way to tell if a building has been Warded or Wizard
      Locked is to observe the “W” on the portal. The people
      inside a Ward will not know that the Ward has been removed
      until they observe that the “W” is no longer on the portal.
    </description>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I build a Ward.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>9</level>
    </spell>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Weakness</name>
    <group>Curse</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect will curse the victim to inflict 5 points less
      damage with every weapon attack (minimum damage being zero,
      of course). It will first reduce strength bonuses, then
      weapon proficiencies.

      It affects all weapon damage in the same way, including
      ranged attacks, and regardless of whether the weapon is used
      with one hand or two.

      This effect lasts for ten minutes or until removed with a
      Remove Weakness, Dispel or Purify.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <remove>Remove Weakness</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I curse you with Weakness.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>3</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>15</potion>
    <elixir>15</elixir>
    <gas>20</gas>
    <weapon>25</weapon>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Web</name>
    <group>Binding</group>
    <duration>Line-of-sight</duration>
    <description>
      This spell snares the arms of its victim, binding them
      straight to its sides and immobilizing the victim completely
      from the neck down.

      The victim may talk freely, but may not use any Game Ability
      requiring the use of the arms, including using a weapon or
      shield, casting a spell, or activating a gas globe.

      The victim may not walk, run, or be moved in any way. This
      spell does not prevent the victim from being searched or
      being giving a Killing Blow.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Release</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With mystic force I Web you.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>5</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>25</scroll>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Wither</name>
    <group>Necromancy</group>
    <duration>Ten minutes</duration>
    <description>
      This effect causes the target’s limb to become aged and
      infirm. The limb should be specified by the caster (right or
      left leg or arm).

      If the caster does not specify, or if the effects are from a
      potion, it is the victim’s choice as to which limb to have
      withered; however, you may not choose a limb that has
      already been withered.

      You can have up to four Wither spells active upon you at a
      time. If further Withers are cast upon you, then the
      earliest Wither will be replaced and you must start counting
      the ten minutes from that point.

      No weapon may be wielded by that limb nor may the limb be
      used for locomotion or spellcasting. Only an arm or leg can
      thus be withered. Tentacles or similar appendages are
      considered arms for this purpose. The head, tongue, or any
      other such organs do not count as limbs.

      A Restore or a Purify will heal all withered limbs. A Dispel
      will likewise restore all limbs but will also remove all
      other magics upon the recipient.

      If this spell is cast upon an undead creature, it will have
      the same effect as a Restore has on a living creature.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <remove>Purify</remove>
    <remove>Restore</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>I call upon chaos to Wither your &lt;limb&gt;.</verbal>
      <school>Earth</school>
      <level>6</level>
    </spell>
    <potion>30</potion>
  </effect>

  <effect>
    <name>Wizard Lock</name>
    <group>Eldritch Force</group>
    <duration>Five days</duration>
    <description>
      This spell is identical to a Ward spell except that it is
      cancelled by a Dispel.

      If you wish to upgrade your Wizard Lock into a Ward, you
      must first dispel the Wizard Lock. In all other respects,
      this spell follows all of the rules for a Ward, including
      the use of Lesser Investment.

      The building must be visibly marked with a large “W” to
      indicate the presence of a Ward or Wizard Lock.

      There is no way to tell the difference between a Ward or a
      Wizard Lock just by looking at it; the only way to tell is
      to cast a Dispel at the portal and see if it remains. You
      must have a marshal present in order to do this.
    </description>
    <remove>Dispel</remove>
    <spell>
      <verbal>With eldritch force I build a Wizard Lock.</verbal>
      <school>Celestial</school>
      <level>8</level>
    </spell>
    <scroll>40</scroll>
  </effect>
</effects>
